<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A blazyng starre or burnyng beacon, seene the 10. of October laste (and yet continewyng) set on fire by Gods prouidence, to call all sinners to earnest [and] speedie repentance. Written by Francis Shakelton, minister and preacher of the worde of God.</title>
            <author>Shakelton, Francis.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1580</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11953</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22272</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117156</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852371</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852371</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17687</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11953)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17687)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 470:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A blazyng starre or burnyng beacon, seene the 10. of October laste (and yet continewyng) set on fire by Gods prouidence, to call all sinners to earnest [and] speedie repentance. Written by Francis Shakelton, minister and preacher of the worde of God.</title>
                  <author>Shakelton, Francis.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[70] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ihon Kyngston, for Henry Kirkham, and are to bee solde, at the signe of the blacke boye, adioynyng to the little northdore [sic] of sainct Paule,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1580.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: a⁴ A-D (-D8).</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A blasyng starre or burnyng beacon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>C2 in facsimile by Burt.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Omens --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Comets --  1580 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17687:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17687:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A blazyng Starre or <hi>burnyng Beacon, ſeene the 10. of</hi>
               </hi> October laſte (and yet continew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng) ſet on fire by Gods prouidence, to call all ſinners to earneſt &amp; ſpeedie repentance. Written by <hi>Francis Shakelton,</hi> Miniſter and preacher of the worde of GOD.</p>
            <figure/>
            <q>¶I will ſhewe wonders in heauen and in the earth, bloud, and fire, and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of ſmoke. <bibl>Ioel. 2, 30.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>¶ Imprinted at London by Ihon Kyngston, for Henry Kirkham, and are to bee ſolde, at the ſigne of the blacke boye, adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng to the little Northdore of ſainct Paule. <hi>1580.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17687:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17687:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the right Honorable <hi>ſir Thomas Bromley knight, lord</hi>
               </hi> Chauncellour of Englande, and one of her Maieſties moſte honourable pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie Councell, long life and health, with increaſe of honor, and all maner of ſpirituall bleſſynges.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T maie be demed in the iudgement of the worlde, a great preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in me (right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable) thus vnaduiſedly to adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture the diſcourſe of this late blazing Starre, whiche appeared the x. daie of October laste 1580. whereof verie ſmall (or rather no
<pb facs="tcp:17687:3"/> accompt at all) is made emong the vulgare ſort, for that it hath not altogether ſuche ſple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dant bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and glisteryng radiation, as ſome other Cometes heretofore haue had. I knowe (I ſay) I ſhalbe launced with the bitter reproofes and Zoilous reprehenſions of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine fine mouthed mates, who looke for finer phraſes, and more mellow and ſugred ſentences, then my poore ſkill or habilitie will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford. My onely drift herein (right Honourable) is to diſſwade the worlde, from freezing in the dreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of their ſynnes, by admoniſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng them of the finall diſſolution of the Engine of this worlde, and
<pb facs="tcp:17687:3"/> ſeconde commyng of Christ in the cloudes, whiche by many manifeſt and ineuitable reaſons J gather, can not bee farre of. Jn respecte whereof, accordyng to the duetie of my profeſſion, J exhort all men to awake out of their ſlepe by ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt repentance, whiche is the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte and plain path waie to auert Goddes iuste plagues, deſeruedly threatened vnto vs. The artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all deſcription of whiche Starre, together with his appearance, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, colour, continuance, mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, forme, ſignificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and effect, as J by the aduiſe of ſome right ſkilfull in the Mathematiques, haue (by the waie) ſuperficiallie
<pb facs="tcp:17687:4"/> touched: So dooe J leaue the fuller delineation thereof to them, who profeſſedly dwell in the ſame Art, (Astronomie I meane) &amp; are beſt hable to yeeld their learned reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions. My profeſſion drawyng me an other waie, requireth an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther maner of methode, which as J haue here to my poore ſkill diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered: So am J with all humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, moste duetifully to craue your Honors pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for the acceptance thereof at my handes, till it ſhall pleaſe God to enhable me with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther opportunitie, to preferre vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Lordſhippes cenſure, ſome other woorke of greater momente &amp; importance. Till then, alwaies
<pb facs="tcp:17687:4"/> J ſhall humblie beſeeche the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to preſerue your good Lordſhippe with honour, healthe and all felicitie to his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors moste hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Francis Shakelton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:17687:5"/>
            <head>¶ Jn hanc Franciſci Shakeltonj Cometologiam, Ogdoastichon.</head>
            <l>ECce Shakeltonj non parua volumine paruo</l>
            <l>Commoda, Brutigenis hexapla certa ſuis.</l>
            <l>Eia agè lector: in hoc forſan reperire libello</l>
            <l>Multa potes, tibi quae vix aliunde patent.</l>
            <l>Vt tibi &amp; vt patriae prodeſſet amicus amicae,</l>
            <l>Participem terſi te facit eſſe ſtyli.</l>
            <l>Tu tantùm grates memor eſto rependere dignas,</l>
            <l>Sic fructum ſtudij demetet ipſe ſui.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Newton, Cestreſhyrius.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:17687:5"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O often as there hath been at any time ſene eclipſes of the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne or the Moone, either any Comette, or bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng Starre in any parte of the Heauen: Thoſe that are Chriſtians, haue forthwith been taught by Chriſte hymſelf to lifte vp their heades,<note place="margin">Luke. 21.28.</note> knowyng that their redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption draweth nigh (that is to ſaie) Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are admoniſhed thereby, that the daie of Iudgement is at hande: When thei ſhall ſee the Sonne of manne commyng in the Cloudes with power and greate glorie, to iudge the quicke and the deade, and to giue to euery man accordyng to his deedes, that thei haue doen in their bodies, be thei good or euill.<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.10.</note> Whoſe comming ſhalbe (as Peter ſaith) as a theefe in the night: In the which daie, the Heauen ſhall paſſe awaie with a noyce, and the Elementes ſhall melte with heate, and the yearth with the workes that are therein ſhall bee burnt vp (whiche is as muche to ſaie) that all the worlde ſhall bee conſumed, accordyng to the ſaiyng of our
<pb facs="tcp:17687:6"/> Sauiour Chriſte:<note place="margin">Math. 24.35.</note> Heauen and yearth ſhall paſſe awaie, but my wordes ſhall not paſſe awaie.<note place="margin">Ariſt. lib. de caelo. &amp; lib. 8. Phiſ.</note> Yet notwithſtandyng I am not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, how that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> the Prince of all thoſe Philoſophers (whiche the Latiniſtes doe call <hi>(Peripatetici)</hi> doth labour very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to proue that the worlde is eternall: meanyng thereby that it hath no beginning neither ſhall it haue any endyng. Of this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion is <hi>Galenus</hi> alſo (that moſte experte Phiſition of <hi>Pergamus</hi> a citie of <hi>Aſia</hi>) who liued in thoſe daies that <hi>Marcus</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modus</hi> were Emperors,<note place="margin">Galenus.</note> and dreamyng al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the perpetuitie and continuance of the worlde, ſaith after this maner: <hi>Se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>per ita ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit, ſic igitur perdurabit.</hi> Moreouer <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> writeth thus:<note place="margin">Manilius.</note> 
               <hi>Non alium videre patres, alumne ne potes aſpicient?</hi> (that is to ſay) our Fathers haue ſeene no other worlde, and ſhall our Nephewes ſee any other? &amp;c. Moreouer you ſhall vnderſtande, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Latiniſtes,<note place="margin">Plinie.</note> 
               <hi>Plinie</hi> doth alſo main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine this opinion, affirming <hi>Mundum eſſe aeternum, immenſum, neque genitum, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que interiturum vnquam.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auerrois. lib. 1. de caelo.</note> And in like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>Auerrois</hi> a follower and imitator of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17687:6"/> doeth tread ſo right in his Maiſters ſteppes, that in his firſte booke <hi>De caelo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem ſuper. 8. Phiſ. Ariſt.</note> he diſputeth earneſtly againſt thoſe, who doe acknowledge that the worlde was created &amp;c. Declaryng alſo the ſame thyng in his Commentaries, where he doeth expounde and defende the argument of his Maiſter <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> concerning the eternitie, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuitie of the worlde.</p>
            <p>I am not vnmindfull alſo of thoſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des whiche Peter doeth alledge in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the vngodly and wicked worldlinges,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.4.</note> ſaiyng: Where is the promiſe of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng? For ſince the fathers dyed, all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges continue alike from the beginnyng of the creation. But ye ſhall vnderſtande, that all theſe prophane and wicked reaſons, and Heathniſhe and vnfruitfull queſtions, ſhall bee confuted orderly God willyng in their places, by the authoritie of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>Knowe ye therefore firſt deare Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that almightie GOD hym ſelf doeth teache vs, by his holie Prophettes and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles: but moſte ſpecially by his onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Soonne (<note place="margin">Hebr. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.2.</note> whom he hath made heire
<pb facs="tcp:17687:7"/> of all thinges) that the worlde was created of nothyng, and ſhall returne into nothyng againe. And therefore wee muſt not onely beleeue it,<note place="margin">Read. Gene. 14.19. cap. 20.11. cap. 31.17</note> but alſo defende the ſame to bee ſo, as he hath vndoubtedly ſpoken it.</p>
            <p>And to the ende that out of many teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, a fewe maie bee recited, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Moiſes beyng a liuely witneſſe of this matter, hath deſcribed the woorke of the creation of the worlde after this maner, ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng:<note place="margin">Nehem. 9.6. Iob. 2.9. Gene. 1.1.</note> In the beginnyng GOD created the heauen and the yearth, &amp;c. The Prophetes alſo followyng Moiſes, &amp; maintainyng the ſame truth: doe affirme God to be the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of heauen and yearth Eſpecially Dauid ſaiyng.<note place="margin">Pſal. 89.11.</note> The heauens are thyne, the earth alſo is thyne, thou haſt laied the foundation of the worlde, and all that therein is. Thou haſte created the North and the South &amp;c. And againe:<note place="margin">Pſal. 102.25.</note> Thou haſt aforetyme laied the foundation of the yearth, And the heauens are the worke of thy handes. Thei ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe,<note place="margin">Reade more of this. Pſal. 115.16. Pſal. 135.6.</note> but thou ſhalt endure, euen thei ſhall all waxe olde as doeth a garment, and as a veſture thou ſhalte chaunge them, and thei ſhalbe chaunged, but thou art the ſame, and
<pb facs="tcp:17687:7"/> thy yeres ſhall not faile, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And as the Prophetes haue made men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the creation of the worlde,<note place="margin">Iere. 27.5. and cap. 32.17. Amos. 4.13. Eſay. 43.5. ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 45.12. Zacharie. 12 Actes. 4.24. cap. 24.15. Apoc. 10.6.8. Gene. 7. verſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 19.20.21.22.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 24. Luke. 17.26.</note> ſo haue thei made reherſall of the conſummation of the ſame. Eſpecially Moiſes in the deluge (or the vniuerſall floode) doeth verie nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie deſcribe vnto vs, the type or figure of the conſummation of the world. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Sauiour Chriſte, alludyng vnto the ſame generall deſtruction by his Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt Luke ſaieth. That as it was in the daies of Noe, ſo ſhall it bee in the daies of the Sonne of man. The eate, thei dranke, the married wiues, and gaue in marriage, vnto the daie that Noe went into the Arke. And the flood came and deſtroied them all: Likewiſe alſo as it was in the daies of Lot, thei eate, thei dranke, thei bought, thei ſold, thei planted, thei builte. But in the daie that Lot went out of Sodome, it rained fire and Brimſtone from heauen, and deſtroied the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all. After theſe enſamples ſhall it bee in the daie when the Sonne of man ſhalbe reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, &amp;c. And therefore Chriſt ſaieth, that the harueſt is thende of the worlde.<note place="margin">Math. 13.39 Cap. 28 20.</note> And in like maner: Beholde I am with you alwaie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till
<pb facs="tcp:17687:8"/> the ende of the worlde.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.21.22. 1. Cor. 10.11.</note> Reade more Rom. <hi>8.21.22.</hi> &amp;c. And againe. All theſe thynges were written to admoniſhe vs, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the endes of the worlde are come.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 21.1. 2. Pet. 3.13.</note>Out of all theſe teſtimonies, whiche I haue hetherto alledged (that in the meane ſeaſon I maie omitte that, whiche is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of a newe heauen, and a newe yearth, this maie be concluded. <hi>viz.</hi> That whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer God by his holie Prophetes and ſainc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, hath reuealed vnto the worlde, muſt of neceſſitie bee iuſte and true: But he hath taught vs (by their Miniſterie) that the worlde was not onely created by God, but alſo ſhall hee conſumed by hym: Therefore wee muſt beleeue that the worlde had a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnyng, and ſhall haue an endyng. But that I maie omitte many other reaſons,<note place="margin">Aug. in 28. queſt. in vet. Teſtam.</note> that I could alledge for the maintenaunce of the ſame thyng. I will onely alledge the argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes that <hi>Auguſtine</hi> vſeth in his <hi>28</hi> queſtion of the newe Teſtamente, whoſe woordes are theſe (to the vtter confutation of all thoſe that doe affirme, that the worlde is eternall.)</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The wordes of S. Auguſt.</note>
               <hi>Res aeterna diuerſitatem abhorret, cum
<pb facs="tcp:17687:8"/> ſit nec tactu, nec viſu capienda. &amp;c.</hi> (That is to ſaie) That thyng whiche is euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng, doeth abhorre all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarietie, becauſe it can neither bee felt, nor ſene (ſeeyng that it is without a bodie.) But the worlde is ſubiect to paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, becauſe that water doeth ſtriue againſt fire, and fire (if it doe abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de) dooeth ouercome the water. And for as muche as the yearth is colde and drie, and maie bee burned, becauſe it is <hi>Res copora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis:</hi> therefore it is a foule abſurditte to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that the worlde is eternall. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But lettyng theſe thinges paſſe, it ſhall manifeſtly be proued that this worlde ſhall periſhe and paſſe awaie, if wee doe but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the partes whereof it doeth conſiſt, for doe we not ſee the yearth to be changed and corrupted? Sometymes by the inundation of waters? Sometymes by fiers? And by the heate of the Sunne? And doe we not ſée that ſome partes of the ſame doe waxe old, and weare awaie euen for verie age? Doe wee not in ſome places alſo read, that mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines haue falne doune, by reaſon of earth quakes? And Rockes haue been cracked, and broken ſo in peeces, that by the meanes
<pb facs="tcp:17687:9"/> thereof, certaine Riuers haue been (as it were dronke vp, or els, haue had recourſe an other waie? Alſo haue ye not read, that the ſeas haue rebounded backe, &amp; ouerwhelmed whole Cities, and vtterly drouned whole Prouinces? And what are theſe ſtrange al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations els, but euident argumentes that the worlde ſhall one daie haue an ende?</p>
            <p>Naie I dooe ſaie moreouer, that if wee will giue credite to the Mathematiques, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> conſtitution of the celeſtiall worlde, is not theſame that it hath been in tymes paſte, for ſo muche as the Sunne, is not ſo farre diſtant from vs now, as it hath been here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore. So that ſome dooe affirme, that the diſtance betwéene the Sonne and the earth (whiche is the centre of the worlde) is leſſe now, by the fourth part almoſt, then it was in the tyme whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Ptolomeus</hi> liued. Where hence thei dooe coniecture and gather, that the Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne (at this daie) is nerer vnto vs by <hi>9976.</hi> German miles then it was before.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, if there be ſo greate altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the ſuperior worlde, what ſhall wee ſaie of the inferiour? Let this therefore be a forcible argument to proue, that the world
<pb facs="tcp:17687:9"/> ſhall haue an ende: for ſo muche as it doeth waxe old, and euery part thereof doeth feele ſome debilitie and weakeneſſe. For there is leſſe vertue in Plantes &amp; hearbes then euer was before: And more feeble ſtrength in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery liuing creature then euer was before. And leſſe age in men then euer was before. It remaineth therefore (of neceſſitie) that ſhortly there ſhall be an ende and conſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the worlde, becauſe it is (as it were) ſubiecte to olde age, and therefore feeble in euery parte.</p>
            <p>But it is not ſufficient for me to affirme that there ſhalbee an ende, but I muſt alſo proue the maner of the ende of the worlde, whiche ſhall bee by fire: accordyng as it is written <hi>2.</hi> Peter. <hi>3.7.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.31.</note> The heauens and the earth whiche are now, are kepte by the ſame worde in ſtore, and reſerued vnto fire againſt the day of Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of vngodlie men. But if ye doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde of me, how the heauen that now is and the yerth ſhalbe burned with fire? The aunſwere is eaſily made that it ſhalbee <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> formam, non ſecundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſentia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> (As the Philoſophers and the Diuines dooe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme.
<pb facs="tcp:17687:10"/> Accordyng to the ſaiyng of Paule. <hi>Praeterit ſigura huius mundi.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.31.</note> Whereunto I might adde the Iudgement of Heathen writers, whiche ſhalbee verie profitable to be conſidered of thoſe that are conuerſant in the readyng of <hi>Ouide.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ouid. lib. 1. metamorp.</note> 
               <hi>lib. 1. Metamorpho.</hi> where (ſpeakyng of Iupiter) he ſaith thus. <q>
                  <l>Eſſe quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in fatis reminiſcitur affore te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pus,</l>
                  <l>Quo mare, quo rellus, correpta<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> regia coeli,</l>
                  <l>Ardeat, &amp; mundi moles operofa laboret,</l>
               </q> Of the ſame thyng reade <hi>Lucane</hi> alſo <hi>lib. i.</hi> Who dooeth as it were appoint a certaine hower, wherein all the worlde ſhalbee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed and brought to nothyng, ſaiyng: <q>
                  <l>Sic cum compage ſoluta.</l>
                  <l>Saecula tot mundi ſuprema coegerit hora,</l>
                  <l>Antiquum repetens iterum chaos, oi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>a miſtis,</l>
                  <l>Sydera ſyderibus concurrent ignea pontum</l>
               </q> 
               <hi>Aſtra petent &amp;c.</hi> Wherunto I doe referre that whiche Peter doeth ſet doune vnto vs, ſaiyng:<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.20.</note> The heauens ſhal paſſe awaie with a noiſe, and the Elementes ſhall melt with heate, and the yearth with the workes that are therein, ſhalbe burnt vp by ſire (as hath bin before declared.) <hi>Vbi figura mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terit non natura.</hi> For whiche cauſe the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb facs="tcp:17687:10"/> of the Sentences dooeth affirme,<note place="margin">Magiſter ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia. lib. 4. diſt. 47.</note> that the qualities of the corruptible elementes, whiche were ſomtymes agreable vnto our corruptible bodies, ſhould bee burnt vp vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlie in the generall conſummation. And the ſubſtance of thoſe Elementes ſhall haue theſame qualities, whiche through a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelous mutation, ſhall agree with immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall bodies. This ſentence was borowed out of <hi>Auguſtine lib. xx. cap. xvj. de ciuitate Dei.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. lib. 20 cap. 16. de ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitate dei.</note> And ſeeyng that wee haue proceaded thus farre, I thinke it not to bee muche a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe for me, to ſpeake ſomwhat of the time when this daie of Doome, or generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation of the worlde ſhalbe.</p>
            <p>Knowe ye therefore, that the Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques dooe dreame of a greate yere, after the whiche all the Starres ſhall retourne, <hi>Ad ſua principia.</hi> And then thei ſaie, that the ende of the worlde ſhould immediatly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe. And their opinion is, that heauen and yearth ſhalbe burned, when all the Starres whiche doe now obſerue, diuers and ſonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie courſes, ſhall mete together in the ſigne <hi>Cancer.</hi> Euen as <hi>Beroſus</hi> that <hi>Chaldaean</hi> Aſtronomer dooeth affirme, that the firſte
<pb facs="tcp:17687:11"/> age (in the daies of Noe) was drouned, when all the Starres had their concurſe and meetyng together, in the ſigne called <hi>Capricornus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Naie there haue been ſome in this our age, that haue gone about to appoint a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine yere, when this daie ſhould bee. (As <hi>Hoſiander</hi> and <hi>Stiphelius</hi> did) but thei wer deceiued,<note place="margin">Hoſiander Stiphelius.</note> by the erronious ſpirite of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſtes, inſpired into them by Sathan, who is altogether delighted in lyes, &amp; erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s thereby (if it were poſſible) entendyng to deceiue all thoſe, that thurſte after the ſimple truthe, whiche is onely founde in the ſacred Scriptures, wherein there is no mention made at all of the dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or the continuaunce of the worlde.</p>
            <p>I knowe alſo that there bee certaine, whiche doe deuide the worlde into ſixe ages The firſte from Adam vnto Noe. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond from Noe vnto Abraham: The third from Abraham vnto Dauid: The fowreth from Dauid vnto the tranſmigration into Babilon: The fifte from the tranſmigratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto Chriſt. And the ſixt and laſte from the Incarnation of Chriſt vnto the ende of the
<pb facs="tcp:17687:11"/> worlde. Wherefore thei alledge, that ſeyng that age wherein now wee liue, is the laſte age, it maie be verie fitly called <hi>aetas decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pita,</hi> a crooked age. Seyng that the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt Ihon doeth terme it the laſte howre,<note place="margin">1. Ihon. 1.18.</note> but yet neuertheleſſe, how long that age (or howre) ſhall endure, is kept fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of all men.</p>
            <p>I am not ignoraunt, yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng, how ſome (beeyng moued thereunto through certaine weake and feeble coniec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures) haue (as it were) appointed out the time of the daie of Iudgement, and ende of the worlde: Bringyng forthe the Oracle of Elias, whiche thei borowe from the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Hebrewes, whereunto many doe giue verie greate credite. And theſe fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes dooe affirme: That the worlde ſhall endure <hi>6000.</hi> yeres: and thei dooe alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide thoſe yeres after this maner. Affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng that <hi>2000.</hi> yeres, ſhould bee conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, before the tyme that almightie God gaue the lawe to Moiſes, &amp; to the reſt of the children of Iſraell. Thei acknowledge alſo that the other twoo thouſande yeres ſhould be ſpent vnder the tyme of the Lawe. And
<pb facs="tcp:17687:12"/> the laſte <hi>2000.</hi> yeres ſhould bee expired in the Kyngdome of Chriſte. And thei adde moreouer that theſe twoo laſte <hi>2000.</hi> ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, ſhall not be fullie finiſhed, the ſynnes of the worlde, ſhould be ſo abundantly encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſhould appeare ſo abhominable in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>I can not forget but that there are other ſome alſo, who haue faigned, that the world ſhall endure ſixe daies, euen as it was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in ſixe daies. But for ſo long tyme as it ſhall endure, thei dooe giue to euery daie a thouſande yeres (whiche commeth all to one rekonyng as before). As though the Prophet Dauid would haue it to be ſo?<note place="margin">Pſal. 90.4.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaieth: for a thouſande yeres in thy ſight, are as yeſterdaie when it is paſte, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Other ſome alſo are founde, who dooe thinke that the miſticall bodie of Chriſte (that is to ſaie his Churche) ſhall liue the ſpace of <hi>33.</hi> yeres vpon the yearth, becauſe Chriſte hymſelf liued ſo long in the worlde after he had taken his humaine bodie of the Virgine Marie: but thei doe adde to euery yere fiftie lackyng one, to make the yeres of <hi>Iubelaei.</hi> But all theſe thinges are but the
<pb facs="tcp:17687:12"/> fooliſhe inuentions, and dreames of mortall men. And (without all doubt) it is a miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and moſte lamentable caſe, that we ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng ſo many plaine, and manifeſt, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable teſtimonies in the holie Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, concernyng Faithe, Hope, and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and other Godlie and Chriſtian offices and dueties: wherein there is no obſcuritie or darkneſſe at all, that wee doe altogether neglecte I ſaie, and deſpiſe them as mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not worthie the talkyng of, and with ſo greate diligence and paines (I will not ſaie ſuperſtition) wil ſeme to proſecute and buſie our heades aboute ſuche vnfruitfull queſtions, as are no whit appertainyng to our Saluation. But ſuche is the wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and curioſitie of our age and tyme. That as the Apoſtle ſaieth:<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.4.</note> Euery man is puffed, albeeit he knowe nothyng in deede at all, but doteth about queſtions and ſtrife of woordes, whereof commeth enuie, ſtrife railynges, euill ſurmiſynges, vaine diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of men endewed with corrupt min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and deſtitute of the truthe, &amp;c. Let vs therefore aunſwere this queſtion (concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng the time when the worlde ſhalbe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed)
<pb facs="tcp:17687:13"/> with <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and conclude after this maner <hi>(viz)</hi> that this is altogether a vaine, friuolous, and vnfuitfull queſtion. For if it were conuenient, and meete for vs to knowe the tyme, who might more bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter enſtructe vs in this poincte, then our Sauiour Chriſte hymſelf? who made aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere vnto his Diſciples (when thei vſed this queſtion in his preſence, ſaiyng vnto hym.<note place="margin">Actes. 1.6.</note> Lorde wilt thou at this tyme reſtore the kyngdome to Iſraell? And he ſaied vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them: It is not for you to knowe the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes or the ſeaſons, whiche the Father hath put in his owne power, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This aunſwere whiche thei did receiue of Chriſte, a man would thinke would ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice any Chriſtian, ſeyng Chriſte his owne Diſciples, did neither enquire of the houre, the daie, or the yere, but ſimplie propoſed their queſtion of the tyme, vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt made an excellent aunſwere, as is afore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared. Agreeable vnto whiche place is the teſtimonie of Chriſt Ieſus hymſelf, ſaiyng Of that daie and of that howre knoweth no man,<note place="margin">Math. 24.36. Math. 13.32.</note> no not the Angels that are in heauen, (neither yet the ſonne of man) but the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:17687:13"/> onely. And again Paule ſaieth.<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 5.1.</note> Of the tymes and ſeaſons brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue no néede that I doe write vnto you: for you your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues knowe perfectly, that the daie of the Lorde ſhall come euen as a Theefe in the night. For when thei ſhall ſaie peace and ſaffetie, then ſhall come vpon them ſodaine deſtruction: as the trauaile vpon a woman with child, and thei ſhall not eſcape. But ye brethren are not in darkneſſe, that that daie ſhould come vpon you as it were a Theef. Ye are all the children of light, and the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the daie, wee are not of the night, neither of the darkeneſſe. Therefore let vs not ſleepe, as others doe, but let vs watche and be ſober, &amp;c. For it is in vaine for vs to goe aboute to make a computation of thoſe yeres, whiche are remainyng in this world or to appoincte the daie, or howre, yere, or tyme when it ſhalbe conſumed? Seeyng it is not our partes and duties to knowe, and ſearche theſe thinges: as we haue heard out of the mouthe of the truthe hymſelf Chriſte Ieſus. Wherefore albeeit the Deuill our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon aduerſarie, doeth labour by all mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to fill our heades, with infinite and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable
<pb facs="tcp:17687:14"/> queſtions (ſettyng a ſide all ſuche as are neceſſarie for our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) yet let vs that are Chriſtians, prepare our ſelues to watchfulneſſe, and Chriſtian meditation and praiers: ſo often as we dooe heare any me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion of the daie of Iudgement, for feare leaſt when Chriſte our Maiſter commeth, he finde vs ſleepyng, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Let vs therefore ſtaie, and reſt our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues here, not ſeekyng curiouſly into the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretes of almightie God, againſte his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine will and pleaſure. And yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng, to the ende we maie bee perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the certaintie therof, and of Chriſtes godlie care and brotherlie loue and affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhewed towardes vs: He hath lefte behynde hym ſome thyng in the woorde of GOD, concernyng this matter, whiche is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for our comforte, and enſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Math. 24.22.</note>Firſt, that thoſe daies ſhalbe ſhortened for the electes ſake. Whereby he doeth giue vs to vnderſtande, that the nomber of thoſe yeres ſhall not bee accompliſhed, and fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, whiche otherwiſe were appoincted, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the conſummation of the worlde.</p>
            <p>Secondly theſame Chriſte, hath added,
<pb facs="tcp:17687:14"/> thus muche for our learnyng, that ſeyng it is not expedient for vs, to knowe the tyme of the conſummation of the worlde: yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, there ſhould appeare certain ſignes and tokens of theſame, by the courſe whereof we maie eaſily coniecture of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentes followyng. Whereby our Sauiour Chriſte hath declared, not onely his ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler loue whiche he beareth towards vs: but alſo ſheweth how muche he dooeth tender our ſaluation, in that he doeth ſende ſignes and tokens, in heauen and in Earth, as the forerunners of his ſeconde commyng vnto Iudgemente. Whereof ſome are partly knowne of vs, becauſe thei are familier vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our ſences: and ſome of them alſo are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wonted and ſtrange, ſo that we maie true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaie, that it pleaſeth almightie God, by ſuche monſters of Nature, to admoniſhe vs of our dueties, and obedience, whiche wee owe vnto his diuine Maieſtie. For as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſee the body of man (whiche is the priſon of the ſoule) to be ſubiecte to many infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: As namely, when we ſée the haire of a mannes head, to beginne to ſhed and fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie, or els to waxe white: the eyes to wax
<pb facs="tcp:17687:15"/> bleared, and dimme of ſight: The ſtomack to bee weake, and vnapte to digeſtion: the eares to be deffe, the tongue to falter: The knées to be ready to bowe vnder a manne: and all the members and partes of manne, to bee féeble and brought into ſubiection (as it were) through Biles, and Vlcers, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſeaſes whatſoeuer, that are incide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the Nature of man: and at the preſent ſight thereof wee can ſaie, that thoſe ſignes dooe preſage, that death is imminent, and not far<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re of from that man: And in like maner, as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſe the tiles of any edifice or buiding to bée broken, the walles to beginne to tot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the roffe to bée ready to fall doune, the poſtes and principall timber to beginne to ſhrinke out of their iointes, the foundation to be rotten, &amp;c. Forthwith we can ſaie that theſame houſe, is ready to decaie and come to vtter ruine, for lacke of a good tenaunt, or Landlorde that ſhould kéepe the ſame in due reparation: Euen ſo can not we chuſe, but confeſſe, that all theſe late horrible, and monſterous monſters of Nature (I ſpeake as well of men, as of bruite beaſtes) whiche are daiely ſeen in this our age: Beſides the
<pb facs="tcp:17687:15"/> manifolde ſtraunge tokens, and vnwonted ſignes, whiche are oftentymes euidently ſeene in the Sonne, and in the Moone, and in the Starres, and in all the hoſte of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: Are (as you would ſaie) the Vlcers, and Biles, naie I maie ſaie plainlie, the blaines of the whole worlde: and doe verie notablie prognoſticate, and foreſhewe vnto vs, the vniuerſall diſſolution, and deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſame.</p>
            <p>No leſſe then the Starre that ſtoode o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Hieruſalem like vnto a Sworde, (and alſo the ſtraunge Comet whiche endured for the ſpace of a whole yere: the Deuill in the figure and ſhape of a man: An armie of ſouldiours ſeene in the cloudes, marchyng about the citie, with a nomber of horſemen and chariotts: with this voice y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was heard in the Temple, ſaiyng: <hi>Lett vs goe hence.</hi> Beſides other euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and vgly ſhapes, &amp;c.) did foreſhewe and Prognoſticate vnto the Iewes, the deſtruction that ſhould come vpon the Citie of Hieruſalem, and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitauntes thereof. Who contemned not onely theſe demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrations of their deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (that was imminent): but alſo like blind
<pb facs="tcp:17687:16"/> and ſenceleſſe beaſtes, would not giue cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite vnto thoſe wordes, whiche Chriſt hym ſelf, (while he was conuerſant in the earth) did vtter againſt Hieruſalem. Who when he was come nere vnto it,<note place="margin">Luke. 19.41.</note> he behelde it, and wept for it, ſaiyng: O if thou haddeſt, euen knowne at the leaſte in this thy daie, thoſe thinges which belong vnto thy peace. But now are thei hid fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thine eyes, for the daies ſhall come vpon thee, that thyne enemies ſhall caſte a trenche aboute thee: and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe thee rounde, and kéepe thee in on eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſide: And ſhall make thee euen with the ground, and the children whiche are in thée: and thei ſhall not leaue in thee, a ſtone vpon a ſtone, becauſe thou kneweſt not the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of thy viſitation.</p>
            <p>All whiche thynges came to paſſe four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeres iuſte after the paſſion of Chriſte,<note place="margin">Anno dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i 73.</note> who, in his life tyme, (through his Diuine power) foreſawe thoſe thinges, ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen whiche he foreſhewed, in that Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. And with weepyng teares, (as the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt Luke doeth witneſſe) he bewai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led their greeuous miſerie.<note place="margin">Ioſephus lib. 6. cap. 11. de bello Iudaico</note> And therefore, our Sauiour Chriſt, did not without iuſte
<pb facs="tcp:17687:16"/> cauſe vpbraide the Iewes, for their impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencie, and hardneſſe of harte, and vnbelefe when he ſaieth vnto them: O Hieruſalem,<note place="margin">Math. 23.37.</note> Hieruſalem, whiche killeſt the Prophetes, and ſtoneſt them whiche are ſent vnto thee, how often would I haue gathered thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren together, as the Henne gathereth her Chickens vnder her winges, and ye would not? Behold therefore your habitation ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bee lefte vnto you deſolate, &amp;c. And in deede it came ſo to paſſe, for accordyng to the ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng of Chriſt, there was ſo greate diſtreſſe within the lande of Iuda: and Gods wrath was ſo heauie ouer the people of Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that thei were ledd captiue into all Natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and were trodden doune vnder the feete of the Gentiles, &amp;c.<note place="margin">Luke. 21.24.</note> And what other thyng was this I praie you but a greeuous ruine and deſtruction of the Iewes? Beeyng alſo a liuely figure of the conſummation of the whole worlde: whiche I am certainly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded is not farre of. For as our Sauiour Chriſte, before Hieruſalem was beſieged, and deſtroied,<note place="margin">Luke 21.20.</note> did vſe theſe wordes vnto the Iewes: When ye ſee Hieruſalem beſieged with ſouldiers, then vnderſtande, that the
<pb facs="tcp:17687:17"/> deſolation thereof is neere, (and it came ſo to paſſe.<note place="margin">Luke. 21.20.</note>) Euen ſo lett vs bee perſwaded that if thoſe ſignes, whiche Chriſte hath ſhewed, ſhould goe before, his ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng to Iudgement: haue manifeſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, in the ſight of all men, and can not be denied, but that thei are already fulfilled: there remaineth nothyng then, but that we ſhould looke for the ſonne of man to come in the cloudes, with power and greate glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Let vs therefore, conſider the nomber of the ſignes, whiche are mentioned in the holie Scriptures, whiche are called either, <hi>ſigna precedentia, vel concomitantia mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di interitum</hi> (that is) either ſignes goyng before, or els the ſignes that ſhalbee ioyned with the conſummation of the world. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the whiche ſignes: Read that place where Chriſte his Diſciples came vnto hym a parte,<note place="margin">Math. 24.3.</note> ſaiyng. Tell vs when theſe thynges ſhalbee, and what ſigne ſhalbee of thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng, and of the ende of the worlde? Vnto whom Ieſus made aunſwere,<note place="margin">Verſe. 4.</note> and ſaied: take heede that no man deceiue you: For many ſhall come in my name, ſaiyng: I am Chriſt, and ſhall deceiue many. And
<pb facs="tcp:17687:17"/> you ſhall heare of warres, and rumours of warres: ſee that you bee not troubled, for al theſe thynges muſte come to paſſe, but the ende is not yet: For Nation, ſhall ariſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Nation, &amp; Realme againſt Realme and there ſhalbe Famine, and Peſtilence, and earthquakes, in diuers places.</p>
            <p>Now if we will examine our owne ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and rippe vp our owne hartes, we can not denie, but that theſe thynges haue been already fulfilled, whiche Chriſte hath here foreſpoken: call therefore to remembrance that where as Chriſte ſaieth: firſt, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhall come, in my name, ſaiyng: I am Chriſte, &amp;c.) How that in the third yere of the raigne of the Queenes Maieſtie,<note place="margin">Anno. 1561.</note> the tenth daie of Aprill, one Willyam Geffray was whipped fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Marſhalſie in South warke, to Bedlem: for that he profeſſed one Ihon Moore to bee Chriſte our Sauiour. And you ſhall finde that the ſame Ihon Moore alſo, was whipped, vntill he had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, Chriſte to be in heauen, and hymſelf to be a ſinfull man.</p>
            <p>As touchyng the rumor of warres, and the riſyng of Nation againſt Nation: and
<pb facs="tcp:17687:18"/> Realme againſt Realme, the greetious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaſion, and daiely ſiege, that the Turke maketh againſt Chriſtendome, the bloodie broiles betweene the kyng of Spaine, and the Eſtates of the lowe Countries, the bloodie battell fought betweene the Kyng of Portugale, and <hi>Amole Moluco</hi> Kyng of <hi>Feſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anno. 1578. Auguſt 4.</note> and diuers other worthie perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. The preparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Pope into Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, the Ciuile warres and late bloudie Maſſacres made in Fraunce, alſo the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent warres betweene Englande and the rebelles of Ireland, can witneſſe, that theſe ſignes are alſo come to paſſe alreadie.</p>
            <p>Concernyng Famine, thinke vppon the dearth of Corne that was in the fifth yere of Queene Marie, when Wheat was ſold for fowre Markes the quarter, and people were driuen to eate bread made of Acorns, but eſpecially (which is the greateſt dearth of all) call to mynde, the Famine of the woorde of God, whiche could not then bee preached, but in corners, ſo that the people had well nere periſhed, for want of Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall foode.</p>
            <p>As touchyng the Peſtilence, whether
<pb facs="tcp:17687:18"/> that hath not raigned in many places of the worlde of late: call to mynde the yere of the Lorde God <hi>1563.</hi> wherein from the firſte of Ianuarie <hi>1562.</hi> vntill the laſte of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember followyng, there died of the plague within the Citie of London, and liberties thereof <hi>20146.</hi> As the Chronicles doe witneſſe. That I maie omitte to ſpeake of the Peſtilence that was ſince in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the realme, as namely in Norwitch, Rye. &amp;c. Alſo of the plague that is now in Paris, where there dieth <hi>3000.</hi> in a weke. And that in the meane while alſo I ſaie no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng, of that greeuous plague, that hath raigned in Italie, and Spaine, and els where, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, I nede not (I hope) to make any proofe, whether there hath been any yearthquakes already, in ſondrie places of the worlde? Seing that I (am perſwaded) that the remembraunce of the late yearth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, whiche happened the ſixte of Aprill laſte <hi>1580.</hi> is not yet quite forgotten, of thoſe that feare GOD, and thirſt after his commyng. Whiche earthquake ſeemed to be vniuerſall, or at the leaſt, to be perceiued
<pb facs="tcp:17687:19"/> and felte, at that verie tyme, in the moſte parte of Chriſtendome, whiche is miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and wonderfull. Theſe thynges ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whiche our Sauiour Chriſt hath fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhewed to be the foreronners, of his ſeconde commyng, are truely verified, and fulfilled already, ſo that he is altogether blinde, who will not ſe, and (for the moſte part) bereft of his ſenſes, who neither can, nor will vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande theſame. But to proceade (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng all this,<note place="margin">Math. 24.8.</note> whiche hetherto hath been ſpoken.) Chriſte doeth affirme moreouer, that all theſe are but the beginnyng of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes. For then ſhal thei deliuer you (ſaith he) vp to bee afflicted, and ſhall kill you, and you ſhalbe hated, of all nations, for my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes ſake: whiche thyng hath been alreadie verified in the late perſecution, of faithfull Chriſtians, in Queene Maries daies. And ſince that tyme in Fraunce, and Spaine, and other places, there hath been thereof, to muche experience, if the will of GOD had been otherwiſe.<note place="margin">Verſe. 10.</note> More ouer he ſaieth: And then ſhall many bee offended, and ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traie one an other, and ſhall hate one an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And hath there not been many offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="tcp:17687:19"/> bothe giuen and taken? Yea oftenty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes more offence taken, then occaſion hath been giuen? Was there euer the like trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and treacherous conſpiracies, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in any age, As hath been in theſe our daies? And was there euer more bitter hatred ſhowed betwixt one and other, then is at this preſent? I am perſwaded the like enemitie betweene partie and partie was neuer ſeen, as is in this our age? otherwiſe there would not be ſo many brabbling mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſette abroche almoſte in euery Courte in Englande as there be. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Moreouer Chriſte ſheweth that many falſe Prophetes ſhall ariſe, and ſhal deceiue many: for proofe whereof, what ſaie you to the ſwarmes of Anabaptiſtes, whiche doe ſowe their Deueliſhe doctrine almoſte in euery place in the worlde? And is not this verified alſo thinke you? Of the ſecrete re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation of H. N. and of the deueliſhe dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, and curſed doctrine of Dauid George, and Chriſtopher Vitell, and diuers others the cheefeſt Pillers of the familie of Loue? Whoſe bookes of damnable hereſies, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſte diuerſe of the moſte princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall
<pb facs="tcp:17687:20"/> Articles of the chriſtian faithe: are ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered abroad in many places of this realme to the greate diſturbaunce, and breache of that vnitie of faithe, which ought to be kept in the bonde of peace. But tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes be giuen vnto God, the Queenes Maieſtie, by her graue and learned Counſaile, hath taken ſuche order, that not onely all ſuche bookes ſhalbe called in againe: throughout y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole Realme, but alſo that the Sectaries them ſelues ſhall bee attached, and committed to cloſe priſon, there to remain till either, thei ſhalbe purged and cleared of their hereſies, by recantation: or els by the Lawes of the Realme, to ſuffer the iuſte ſentence of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation for their demerites: and to bee condemned as heretiques. The hereſies whiche thei maintain, as thei are infinite in nomber: ſo are thei alſo full of blaſphemie.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1</hi> As namelie, thei affirme that thei dooe liue ſo perfectly, that thei ſynne not.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> Alſo that who ſoeuer is one of their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, is either as perfecte as Chriſte, or els a very Deuill.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> Thirdlie, thei denie with <hi>Arrius,</hi> that Chriſte is equall with the Father, in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
<pb facs="tcp:17687:20"/> and ſubſtance of the Godhead: groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng that opinion out of this place of the Scripture, where Chriſte ſaieth:<note place="margin">Ihon. 14.27.</note> My Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is greater then I. Not conſideryng that Chriſte ſaieth in an other place. I and my Father are one, &amp;c.<note place="margin">Ihon. 10.30.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4</hi> Thei doe affirme, that the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is paſte alreadie with <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus:</hi> Whiche concernyng the truthe haue erred,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.18.</note> and dooe deſtroye the faithe of certaine.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5</hi> Thei do refuſe to ſuffer perſecution for their Religion: becauſe thei ſaie that their bodies are the temples of the holie Ghoſte: wherein thei doe deny the wordes of Chriſt who ſaieth:<note place="margin">Math. 5.10.</note> Bleſſed are thei whiche ſuffer perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for righteouſneſſe ſake, for theirs is the kyngdome of heauen. &amp;c. Theſe with an infinite nomber of other groſſe errours, doe this deueliſhe family of Loue maintain in their blaſphemous bookes, whiche I doe omit for breuities ſake. Onely haue I gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the worlde a taſte of a fewe of their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, that by the conſideration thereof, all men maie maie take heede of the reſte of their Phariſaicall Leuine, and damnable
<pb facs="tcp:17687:21"/> doctrine, whiche is ſet a broche in their ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Bookes firſte made in the Dutche tongue, in the name of H. N. and lately tranſlated into Engliſhe, haue been ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brought ouer from beyonde the Seas into the Realme. The titles whereof are called <hi>Euangeliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Regni<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> or <hi>a Ioyfull Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the Kingdome. Documentall ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences. The Prophecie of Loue. A publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyng of the peace vpon earth,</hi> and diuers others, which (for auoiding of tediouſneſſe) I will not recite at this preſent.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Math. 24. verſe. 12.</note>And furthermore Chriſt ſaieth, ver. <hi>12.</hi> that becauſe iniquitie ſhalbee encreaſed, the loue of many ſhalbe colde, but he that endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to the ende ſhalbe ſaued. Was there e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I praie you more iniquitie? Did ſynne and tranſgreſſion ſo aboundantly raigne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery where, as it doth at this preſent? Was Chriſtian loue and brotherly fellowſhippe, more cold at any time then now? No true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: Suche wickedneſſe at this daie is rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnyng generally, vpon the face of the earth, that if it were not for the electes ſake, that theſe wretched daies ſhould bee ſhortened, it were not poſſible that any fleſhe ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:17687:21"/> bee ſaued. But to conclude, our Sauiour Chriſt addeth verſe <hi>14.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 24.14.</note> That this Goſpell of the kyngdome, ſhalbe preached through the whole worlde, for a witneſſe vnto all Nations, and then ſhall the ende come.</p>
            <p>Now (I hope) that there is no man ſo impudent, that will deny theſe Prophecies of Chriſte, to bee alreadie fulfilled. For ſo muche as the Goſpell hath been ſo vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally, and plentifully preached throughout the worlde, that there is none who ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> excuſe hymſelf in the daie of the lorde, and ſaie that he hath not heard the ſounde of his Goſpell preached, and publiſhed vnto hym by thoſe, which are appointed to be the ſtewardes of ſuche holie miſteries: but rather thei muſt needes confeſſe, that greate hath been the multitude of the Preachers, &amp;c. What rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon can there bee alledged to the contrarie then, but that the conſummation of the worlde is imminent? Seyng that Chriſte who is the truthe, the waie, and the life hath ſpoken it. Of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is written,<note place="margin">Math. 17.5.</note> that a voice came out of a Cloude ſaiyng: This is that my beloued Soonne in whom I am well pleaſed, heare hym. Hereunto I doe adde
<pb facs="tcp:17687:22"/> that, which is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the Apoſtle Paule.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.1.</note>Now wee beſeche you brethren, by the commyng of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, and by our aſſemblyng vnto hym. That you be not ſodainly mooued from your minde, nor troubled neither, by ſpirite, nor by woorde, nor by letter, as it were from vs, as though the daie of Chriſte were at hande. Lette no man deceiue you by any meanes. For the daie ſhall not come, except there come a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partyng firſt (that is to ſaie Apoſtaſie, or a deniall of the Chriſtian faithe) and that the man of ſynne be diſcloſed, euen the ſonne of perditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whiche is an aduerſarie, and exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth hymſelf againſt all that is called God, or that is worſhipped, &amp;c. Well, all theſe ſignes ye ſee, haue been already paſte, and wee can not deny, but that wee haue ſeene, and yet doe daiely ſee an infinite nomber of Antichriſtes, whiche deny the manifeſt and vndoubted truthe, and fall to Poperie, and all abhominable Idolatrie: ſo that the daie of the Lorde can not bee farre of, but muſt needes be at hande.</p>
            <p>Moreouer I beſeche you, harken what Chriſte ſaieth (ſpeakyng of certaine ſignes
<pb facs="tcp:17687:22"/> whiche ſhall goe before the commyng of Chriſt to Iudgement.<note place="margin">Luke. 21.25.</note>) There ſhall bee ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnes then (ſaieth he) in the Sonne, and in the Moone, and in the ſtarres: And againe,<note place="margin">Math. 24.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9.</note> immediately after the tribulation of thoſe daies, ſhall the Sunne be darkened, and the Moone ſhall not giue her light: and the ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ſhall fall from heauen, and the powers of heauen ſhalbe ſhake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Eſay. 13.9.</note> The Prophet Eſay alſo ſaieth thus, Behold the daie of the lorde commeth cruell, with wrathe, and fearce to anger: to laie the lande waſte, and he ſhall deſtroie the ſynners out of it. For the ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of heauen; and the Planettes thereof ſhall not giue their light, the Sonne ſhalbe darkened in his goyng ſorthe, &amp; the Moone ſhall not cauſe her light to ſhine. Of this read more Ezechiell <hi>32.7.</hi> Daniel <hi>7.13. 1.</hi> Cor. <hi>15.2.</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">Iol. 2.31.</note> Alſo the Prophete Ioell ſaieth: that the Sonne ſhalbe tourned into darkeneſſe, and the Moone into bloud, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the greate and terrible daie of the lorde come. By all whiche ſondrie teſtimonies is ſignified, that all the creatures of God, as well in heauen aboue, as in the yearth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, whether it be the Sonne, the Moone,
<pb facs="tcp:17687:23"/> or the Starres: or any parte of the hoſte of heauen aboue, or the yearth beneth: (ſhalbe (as it were ſummo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, to ſummon the whole world, vnto Chriſtes tribunall feate of iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement. Whiche kinde of Sommons, the vngodlie &amp; impenitent ſynners, ſhall euery daie, contemne more and more, vntill the verie Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t daie. Before whiche tyme bothe heauen &amp; earth (notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding) ſhal after a ſorte, reſemble the countenaunce of an angrie Iudge, the rather, to ſtirre vp all wicked ſynners, to repent their vngodlie li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and to tourne vnto the Lorde: Beeyng mooued thereunto, by theſe and ſuche like ſignes, and tokens of Gods wrathe, whiche ſhall euidently appeare, vnto all the whole worlde, before the ende, and conſummation of theſame, (as hath been before declared): And then ſhal thei ſee the Sonne of manne come in a Cloude, with power and greate glorie. Wherefore, let vs diligently call to our remembraunce, whether any of theſe forenamed ſignes bee paſſed, yea or no-(that is to ſaie) whether there haue been, many and verie often Ecclipſes, of the Sonne: and likewiſe of the Moone or whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:17687:23"/> the Starres, haue ſeemed to fall from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Or the powers of heauen, haue been at any tyme moued, or ſhaken, yea, or no? It can not bee denied, but that there hath been of late yeres, more wonderfull and ſtraunge ſightes ſeen, bothe in the Sonne, and in the Moone, and in the ſtarres (cleane againſt the order of nature) then euer was ſeen, in any age here tofore.</p>
            <p>Haue we not read of twoo Moones that ſhined at one tyme, in the ſeuenth yere of kyng Henry the firſt? Did ye neuer heare tel, of thoſe fiue Moones that ſhined at once in the ſeconde yere of kyng Henry the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth? Haue yee not founde in the Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, how that the Sonne hath appeared, as red as bloud, and ſo continued the ſpace of ſixe howers the laſte daie of October, in the fiftene yere of Kyng Edward the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde? But to come more nerer to our time haue ye not heard, how in the yere of the Lorde <hi>1543.</hi> And the xxxv. yere of the raigne of king Henry the eight, there chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced fower Eclipſes, one of the Sonne (the <hi>24.</hi> of Ianuarie) and three of the Moone, whiche was a marueilous thyng to behold.
<pb facs="tcp:17687:24"/> That I maie omit to ſpeake of the ſtrange Eclipſes of the Sonne and Moone, theſe yeres laſte paſte. But becauſe, I haue he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſpoken ſufficiently of ſignes and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens, whiche haue been ſeen in the Sonne, and in the Moone: for ſo muche as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uior Chriſt,<note place="margin">Math. 24.29.</note> doeth make mention alſo, that the Starres ſhall fall fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen, I thinke it moſte meete and conuenient for me, to ſpeake ſomewhat of blaſing Starres: And ſo muche the rather, becauſe at this preſent ſo iuſte occaſion is offered vnto me, by the reaſon of a blaſyng Starre, whiche did appeare, at the firſte, in the Iudgement of thoſe, whiche are learned <hi>Aſtronomers,</hi> in the ſigne called <hi>Piſces,</hi> the tenth daie of October <hi>1580.</hi> and was left in <hi>Aquarius,</hi> (The motion thereof beeyng retrograde, contrarie to the common courſe of other moueable Starres) and yet doeth it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue ſtill to bee ſeen, and vewed of all men, albeit it doeth not lighten the aire with her glimmering beames, and gliſtring bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo muche as it did at the firſte appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng thereof, beyng ſet on fire by Gods di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine councell, and prouidence, that by the
<pb facs="tcp:17687:24"/> ſight thereof, we might be aduertiſed of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter clappes: And ſo to prepare our ſelues, ſpedely to turne vnto God by faithfull, and vnfeigned repentaunce, that wee maie bee the more readie, to meete hym, in the cloudes with ioye, at his commyng: or els, through the hardneſſe of our harte, whiche can not repent, iuſtly to ſuffer, the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his ſharpe iudgement, and ſo heape vp (as a treaſure vnto our ſelues) wrathe, againſt the daie of wrathe, and of the decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the iuſte Iudgement of God.</p>
            <p>Therefore, in the title of this treatiſe, I doe tearme this Starre, whiche is ſeene at this preſent: A blaſyng ſtarre (or a burning Beacon, &amp;c.) ſet on fire by gods prouidence to warne the whole worlde, of dreadfull warres, betweene God and thoſe, that doe goe on ſtill in wickedneſſe, and will not bee touched, and moued to repentaunce. And I was partely moued, ſo to name it, for this conſideration. For as in Englande (and in moſte places of the whole worlde beſides) Beacons are placed vppon the ſtipeſt and higheſt hills that maie be ſene fartheſt of: &amp; in tyme of warre, and of the inuaſion of the
<pb facs="tcp:17687:25"/> enemie, into any Nation, are (night and daie) watched and ſet on fire, to ſignifie, and declare vnto the inhabitantes thereof, that ſome greate perill and daunger is nigh: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo this Comet, is as it were, ſet on fire in the height of the aire, by the Almightie power and prouidence of our eternall God, to the ende that ſo many as ſhall behold the ſame, maie be admoniſhed and ſtirred vp, by the conſideration therof, to auoide ſuche after clapps, (by their faithfull repentance) as ſhould otherwiſe fall vppon them, in the iuſte Iudgement of almightie God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ariſtotle.</note>I am not ignoraunt, how <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and diuers other Philoſophers, dooe define, a blaſyng Starre, to bee but an yearthly va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour, ſomewhat thicke, and clammie, and fatte in ſubſtaunce, whiche beeyng drawne vp, by little and little, from the bowelles of the yearth, into the vpper region of the aire (nigh to the Sphere, of the fierie element) is there ſet on fire, and through heate made thinne, till it be cleane diſſolued, &amp;c. Whiche opinion of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> albeit it bee thought to bee worthie of credite, and ſubſcription in the iudgement of moſte Philoſophers (who
<pb facs="tcp:17687:25"/> with one conſent, and aſſent, doe agree, that blaſyng Starres dooe ſpryng of naturall cauſes) yet notwithſtandyng all godlie di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, for the moſte part are of this Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the Lorde God hymſelf is the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall aucthour, and principall worker of this Starre (as of all others) makyng it, an immediate meſſenger, and miniſter of his will, accordyng to the tyme, and place, as it beſte pleaſeth his diuine, and eternall maieſtie. Who ſeyng that we, bee ſuche an obſtinate, and ſtiffenecked people, that wee will not bee moued to loue hym: neither in reſpecte of his long ſufferaunce, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng mercie, ſhewed all waies towardes vs: neither yet in reſpecte, of that moſte ſweete, and comfortable voice of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, whiche hath been preached full .xxij. yeres vnto vs, by his faithfull ſeruauntes, and Miniſters: Dooeth now in his ſecrete councell goe an other waie to woorke, and by fearfull Eclipſes of Sonne, and Moone and by gliſteryng flames of fierrie Come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and other ſuche like monſtruous ſignes and tokens in the heauen, and in the earth: doeth goe (I ſaie) about, to enforce and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell
<pb facs="tcp:17687:26"/> vs, (againſt our willes) to be mindfull of the latter daie, whiche is not farre of: If we will giue any credite, to the woordes of Chriſt, who immediatly after, he had made mention, of the ſignes whiche ſhould bee ſene, in the Sonne, and in the Moone, and in the Starres: doeth forthwith adde theſe wordes, <hi>Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haec videritis euenire, cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcite quod prope eſt regnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dei</hi> (That is to ſaie.<note place="margin">Math. 24.33.</note>) When ye ſe all theſe thinges, knowe that the kyngdome of God is nere, euen at the doores.<note place="margin">Luke. 21.28.</note> And againe: when theſe thinges doe beginne to come to paſſe, then looke vp and lift vp your heades: For your redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion draweth nere. Behold the Figge tree, and all trees, when thei now ſhoote forthe ye (ſeyng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) knowe of your owne ſelues, that Sommer is nere: So likewiſe ye whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye ſe all theſe thinges come to paſſe, knowe you, that the kyngdome of God is neare. Verely I ſaie vnto you: This age ſhall not paſſe, till all theſe thynges bee doen: heauen and yearth ſhall paſſe awaie, but my woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſhall not paſſe awaie. By that whiche hetherto hath been ſpoken, you ſee how al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, is not onely the creator, and
<pb facs="tcp:17687:26"/> gouernour of Nature it ſelf, and of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall cauſes, but alſo, he is ſuche a one, as in the worke of this blaſyng Starre, is to bee acknowledged and confeſſed, to bee the onely efficient cauſe. And therefore he one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (and not the blaſyng Starre) is to bee feared, and had in reuerence, conſideryng that he is of power able, not onely, to cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten vs, with temporall puniſhementes, for the amendement of our liues, in this wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched worlde: But alſo, in his Iuſtice, maie condemne vs to eternall death and deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the kyngdome of darkneſſe, where there is euerlaſtyng fire prepared, for the Deuill and his angelles. For whiche cauſe I can not deny, but I muſt needes confeſſe that (for the moſte parte) blaſyng Starres are a token and ſigne of greate horror and feare: and do prognoſticate of ſome ſtrange wonder, and dooe threaten ſome imminent euill, and miſcheefe, commonly vnto that parte of the yearth, towardes the whiche, thei ſeme to caſt their beames moſte direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly. And therfore thoſe Philoſophers, which haue written of the effectes of blaſyng ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, haue founde by good experience, that
<pb facs="tcp:17687:27"/> ſometymes thei dooe ſignifie drouthe, and barronneſſe of the yearth: whiche made <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtinus Niphus</hi> to witneſſe, that after the appearyng of a Comete, <hi>Anno domini 1506.</hi> (whiche was about the <hi>22.</hi> yere of the raigne of kyng Henry the ſeuenth there followed, within twoo yeres after, ſuche a drought in Lumberdie, that from the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of Ianuarie, vnto Nouember after, there fell no Raine at all in that Countrie. Sometymes alſo after the appearyng of blaſyng Starres, there followeth (moſte commonly cruell and greate windes, and mightie te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſtes, with haile ſtones of ſuche a bigneſſe, that through the ſame many houſes are throwne doune, and often times are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed and burned with fire, through the windes: As almoſte the whole countrie of Scotlande, was once waſted by fire the <hi>9.</hi> of Ianuarie. <hi>1251.</hi> a greate Comete of maruelous bigneſſe, hauyng been ſeen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in Scotlande for many daies. <hi>(Anno 1248.)</hi> Sometymes thei dooe ſignifie the death and change of Kynges and Princes, and the alteration of kyngdomes &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealthes: As maie appeare <hi>Anno 1116.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17687:27"/> When Chicheſter was burnte, there was ſene a blaſing ſtarre, &amp; the Moone, not long tyme after, ſemed to bee turned into blood: after the which Maude the Queene of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande died, &amp; was buried at Weſtminſter</p>
            <p>Likewiſe <hi>Anno do. 1165.</hi> appeared a mightie Comete in Scotlande, burnyng out with twoo long beames. And within fourtie daies after died Malcolmus the iiij. Kyng (by name) of the Scottes, as the Chronicle reporteth.</p>
            <p>Moreouer <hi>Anno 1214.</hi> in the moneth of Marche, twoo Cometes of a maruellous bigneſſes verie fearfull to behold, appeared in Scotlande, the one going before, and the other followyng the Sonne, in the whiche yere that moſte happie, and good Kyng Willyam died, after he had rained fourtie and nine yeres.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe <hi>Anno 1538.</hi> appeared a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, after the ſettyng of the Sonne, which was placed in the ſigne <hi>Piſces,</hi> and the taile of it lookyng towardes the Eaſt, and ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly after died the Duke of Saxon.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Anno 1539.</hi> the ſixt daie of Maie appeared a Comete, whiche endured bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng
<pb facs="tcp:17687:28"/> three weekes, and not long tyme af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Iſabell the wife of Charles the fift Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, died in trauaile of childe, in whiche yere alſo died George y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> duke of Saxonie. And in the ſame yere, (as ſome doe write) there appeared three Cometes in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of Aprill, after the whiche the Duke of Cleaue died, and alſo the Buſhop of Trent and diuers other noble perſonages.</p>
            <p>In the yere of the Lorde <hi>1540,</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth daie of Aprill, happened a great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction of the Planettes, and there appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red alſo a marueilous Eclipſe of the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, whoſe beginnyng was before the Sonne riſyng, and did endure in the ſame Eclipſe twoo whole howers after it was riſen. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo there was ſene aboute the ſame tyme, a maruelous ſtraunge Comete in the euen, after the whiche there followed ſo greate a drought, that Hay, Corne, and all kinde of Pulſe were verie ſcarce. And the ſame yere the Caſtell of Prage (a noble Citie in the kyngdome of Bohemia,) with the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall Churche were burned with fire: and many fearfull fires happened in ſonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie places theſame tyme.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17687:28"/>
            <p>Moreouer <hi>Anno 1547.</hi> in Heluecia in Germanie, were ſene in the aire twoo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes of men of warre, and twoo Lions grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly and terriblie fightyng together, ſo long that the one ſemed to bite of the others head quite. And the yere followyng the x. daie of Februarie, was ſene in Saxonie (a Countrie alſo in Germanie) a fire fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, that fell vppon certaine Cities, and twoo hoſtes of menne were ſene in the aire, runnyng and ſkirmiſhyng one againſt an other, beſides diuers other ſtraunge ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, very wonderfull to beholde. And yet in theſe daies it will not ſincke into the heades of many, that there maie any ſuche ſtrange ſight appeare in the aire, becauſe wee can not render a naturall reaſon thereof. And therefore this maketh moſte men to doubt, whether the laſte ſtraunge ſightes, whiche were ſene in Rome <hi>1580.</hi> Ianuarie <hi>18.</hi> and in other places, (the reportes whereof are extante in print to bee ſene) bee true or no?</p>
            <p>Alſo in the yere of our Lorde <hi>1551.</hi> the <hi>28.</hi> daie of Ianuarie, there appeared a bloudie rodde, and ſondrie fearful fires ſéen
<pb facs="tcp:17687:29"/> in the ayre ouer Liſborne, the cheef Citie of Portugall: and there it rained bloud alſo, after the whiche followed ſuche a fearfull yearthquake, that about twoo hundred hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes were greeuouſly ſhaken, and throwne doune, through the fall whereof aboue a thouſande perſones were ſlaine.</p>
            <p>And here alſo I can not forget to ſpeake of that greate blaſing ſtarre, whiche was to ſee to, in forme of a Broome (or a bundell of roddes) whiche appeared in the yere of our Lorde <hi>1531.</hi> the ninth of September ouer Mentz, a Citie in Germanie, whiche did betoken a heauie burthen of Gods venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce, not onely to the ſtate temporall, but alſo to Eccleſiaſticall perſones.</p>
            <p>But to proceade <hi>Anno 1551.</hi> the <hi>21.</hi> of Marche at Madeburge in Germanie, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſeuen of the clocke in the mornyng ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Rainebowes, and three Sonnes were ſene, and in the euenyng the ſame daie thrée Moones.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Anno 1553.</hi> was heard a wofull crie, ſaiyng: <hi>Woe Woe,</hi> twiſe together, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the ſounde of Belles, and the noyſe of Trompettes. And at the ſame tyme it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened,
<pb facs="tcp:17687:29"/> that at Duryngia the Trees and Hearbes, did not onely ſweate bloud: But fearfull noiſes were heard alſo euery night. After the whiche Mauricius the Duke of Saxon, fought in battell with Alberte of Brandenburge, and at the ſame tyme (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng ſmitten with a Bullet) died the thirde daie after the battell.</p>
            <p>Moreouer <hi>Anno 1554.</hi> the firſte daie of Februarie, in the Citie of Catalane in Fraunce, there appeared a marueilous ſight aboute the Moone, like vnto a greate fire, ariſyng from the Eaſte part, and decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng towardes the Weſte: and the Moone it ſelf appeared like to a firebrand in ſight: And moreouer this fire in thaire, did burne with a greate noyſe, and often tymes did caſte forthe flames, and ſparkes of fire: In the like ſorte as a hotte burnyng Iron, is wont to dooe, beeyng beaten vpon a Smi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes handuile.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>26.</hi> daie of Maie followyng it rained bloud alſo, not farre from the toune of Dunckelſpuell in Germanie. Alſo there were ſeene three faire Rainebowes, and ſo many Sonnes and Moones, and two blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
<pb facs="tcp:17687:30"/> Croſſes. And the <hi>11.</hi> daie of Iune fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowyng, aboute fiue miles diſtaunce from Norinberge, in Germanie: there was ſene in the Sonne a bloudie rodde, and many companies of horſemen iuſtlyng together in the aire, whiche ſo did continue, for the ſpace of twoo howers, in ſo muche that it cauſed men greatly to feare, that Doomes daie was at hand: After the whiche ſtrange ſight, Frederick the duke of Saxonie, died the ſame yere. And after that, a notable toune in Germanie, was waſted with fire.</p>
            <p>Alſo in the yere of the lorde <hi>1555.</hi> were ſene in the Citie of Duringia, three Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes the tenth daie of Februarie. And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer at Lune<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>berge was ſeene in the aire, a greate companie of Souldiers, at the right hande of whom there ſtoode an Aungell, holdyng a fierie ſworde in his hande, and a child was there ſeen ſodainly, emongſt the people, which did earneſtly exhort the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple generally, vnto hartie repentaunce: Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmyng Goddes Iudgementes to bee at hande. And when he had thus exhorted the people, he vaniſhed ſodainly out of their ſight, and no manne could afterwardes tell
<pb facs="tcp:17687:30"/> where he was become.</p>
            <p>And in the ſame yere within the boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of Polonia, were heard and ſeene a greate companie of Dogges barkyng and fightyng together, and many of them were torne in peeces. After the whiche fighte, there followed greate warres, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaughter, betweene the inhabitauntes of Polonia, and the Moſcouites.</p>
            <p>Alſo in Duringia (the Sonne ſhinyng cleare) there appeared in the aire, a bright ſworde like vnto a Turkie blade, directing the poinct toward the South, and the edge towardes the Eaſt.</p>
            <p>Moreouer <hi>Anno 1557.</hi> on the nineth daie of Marche, there were ſene thre Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and a verie faire Rainebowe, and the <hi>17.</hi> daie of the ſame monethe followyng, there fell fire from heauen.</p>
            <p>Alſo in an other place, a fierie Globe was ſene: and it rained bloud, in ſo muche that lumpes of bloud, like to the bigneſſe of a mannes hande, did droppe from heauen, in the ſight of many: and in eche droppe were ſene certaine figures, like to mennes faces. And vppon Sainct Laurence daie af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes,
<pb facs="tcp:17687:31"/> the Sonne appeared all blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die: after the whiche the Frenche Kyng fought a greate battaill with Philip Kyng of Spaine. And after that ſaincte Quintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes was taken, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Anno 1558.</hi> there appeared a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie fearfull Comet, whiche continued bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng many weekes. After the appearance of whiche Comete, was ſeene a ſtraunge ſight, and no leſſe fearfull to behold. For the <hi>21.</hi> of Auguſt the daie beeyng cleare, and the weather calme, (twoo howers before Noone) the Sonne beyng then verie clear alſo, was encloſed, about with a greate cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, whiche was of many colours, like vnto a Rainbowe, and continued ſo in ſight for fower howers and a halfe, to the greate feare and amaſement of all ſuche, as beheld theſame. And ſuche a fearfull ſight (as <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarche</hi> reporteth) was ſene before the death of <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer <hi>Anno 1562.</hi> Heauen was ſene to burne in many places of Germanie and a celeſtiall firebrande, ſhined by night in the aire, and ſtretched from the Northe vnto the Southe. Alſo, a greate bande of
<pb facs="tcp:17687:31"/> ſouldiers, were ſeen in the aire, whiche ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſhed muche bloud doune. And in the moneth of Aprill following, the Sonne ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared maruelous bloudie, as well at the riſyng, as at the ſettyng, and continued ſo for three daies together.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Anno 1564.</hi> and in the ſixth yere of the raigne of our gracious Queene Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth, the <hi>7.</hi> of October at night, all the Northe partes of the Element ſeemed to be couered with flames of fire, proceadyng from the Northe Eaſte, and North Weſt, towardes the middeſt of the firmamente, where it ſtaied afterwardes for the ſpace of an hower, and ſo deſcended Weſt.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Anno 1572.</hi> and the <hi>15.</hi> yere of the raigne of the Queenes moſte excellent Maieſtie, the <hi>18.</hi> daie of Nouember in the mornyng, a Starre was ſene Northward, verie bright and cleare in the conſtellation of <hi>Caſſiopeia,</hi> and it ſemed ſo ſtraunge: as from the beginnyng of the worlde, the like was neuer ſene: for in the iudgement of the moſte experte Aſtronomers, (and ſuche as are moſte ſkilfull in the Mathematiques in this our tyme and age) that ſtarre which
<pb facs="tcp:17687:32"/> did then appeare vnto our ſighte, was no Comete, but mere ſupernaturall, directly oppoſite to the Starre, whiche appeared at the Natiuitie of our Sauiour Chriſte, and placed in the verie interſection of <hi>Aequino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctium Terreſtre,</hi> and therefore maie wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely be tearmed or named a ſigne, vnto the whole yearth. As more at large appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in a Booke, whiche was written by that worſhipfull gentleman maiſter Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Digges, called <hi>Alae, ſeu Scalae Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematicae,</hi> where the miracle is by demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations Mathematicall, plainly and moſt manifeſtly proued. Vnto whiche booke I doe referre all thoſe that are deſirous to be reſolued of that Starre ſufficiently.</p>
            <p>Moreouer in the <hi>17.</hi> yere of the raigne of the Queenes Maieſtie, the <hi>14.</hi> daie of Nouember about midnight, diuers ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge impreſſions of fire and ſmoke, were ſene in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aire, to procede forth of a blacke cloude in the North, declinyng towardes the South whiche continued after that maner, vntill the nexte mornyng. And the nexte daie fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowyng, the heauens from all partes did ſeeme to burne, and the flames did meete
<pb facs="tcp:17687:32"/> together ouer the heades of all thoſe, which behelde theſame: and this light burnyng flame, did ſeeme to ariſe as it were, round about from the Horizon.</p>
            <p>Alſo in the yere of our Lorde <hi>1577.</hi> the tenth daie of Nouember at night, there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared a blaſyng Starre in the firmament with a long ſtreame (or taile) proceadyng from theſame, and ſtretchyng the beames thereof directly towardes the Eaſte, verie wonderfull to beholde. And the ſame Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mete endured for the ſpace of <hi>99.</hi> daies, ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng euery night vntill eight of the clocke, that the ſame diſcended: and when the mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter thereof was quite diſſolued, and her ſplendant brightneſſe vtterly extinguiſhed, in the Iudgement of thoſe that bee experte in the rules of Aſtronomie, it reſted it ſelf nere vnto the ſeate of <hi>Caſſiopeia.</hi> The ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes of whiche Starre, are better kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen vnto them then vnto me. But yet in the meane ſeaſon, I would not haue you vnmindfull of thoſe boyſterous blaſtes of windes, and terrible tempeſtes, and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous Snowes: Alſo the greeuous ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrackes, whiche haue happened ſince in
<pb facs="tcp:17687:33"/> moſte places of the worlde, beſide the high floudes, and wonderfull inundations of waters, Morraine of beaſtes, and barron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of grounde, whiche happened not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this Realme of Englande, but in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other countries, ſince the appearyng of the ſame Starre. That in the meane ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon I ſpeake nothyng, of the greate and greeuous ſedicions, and treatourous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies: that haue been put in practiſe in the Regions rounde aboute vs. And all to bryng in Idolatrie and Poperie into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande again (if it were poſſible) which the al mightie God, by the miniſterie of our moſt gracious Prince, and her honorable graue, and wiſe counſaile hath miraculouſly ſtaied hetherto. And I hope ſhall doe, if wee haue grace to be thankfull vnto God for the ſame</p>
            <p>Hetherto ye haue heard (deare Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans) how that by common experience, the flowyng of waters beyonde their boundes, the barronneſſe of the yearth, the ſcarcitie of victualles, the Plague and Peſtilence, with greate windes, and tempeſtes: the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of Common wealthes, and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res betweene Nation and Nation: As al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb facs="tcp:17687:33"/> the late dreadfull yearthquake, with the newe and moſte ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle, and louyng remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce, whiche the Lorde ſent afterwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, throughout diuers places of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but eſpecially in Englande and Spaine, &amp;c. And many other calamities, which happened ſince beſides, maie truely bee named the effectes of the former bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng Starre, whiche was ſeene the tenth of Nouember <hi>1577.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And now hath the Lorde God kindeled an other Starre, this laſte tenth of Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>1580.</hi> the firſte appearyng whereof (with his continuaunce) whiche hath been in <hi>Aquarius,</hi> hetherto hath been before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared vnto you, by the reaſon of the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence that I haue had with thoſe, who are expert in the ſtudie of the Mathematiques: the proceadyng whereof, with his couler, motion, and effectes I leaue onely to their handlyng, whom I knowe to be hable (and I hope alſo are willyng) to reſolue the worlde fullie thereof, when opportunitie ſhal ſerue. In the meane while (that I may vſe no longer delaye) this maie bee conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of a certaintie: that it is the good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb facs="tcp:17687:34"/> and purpoſe of almightie God, (of his inſpeakeable loue and mercie, ſhewed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies towarde vs) that this ſtraunge Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mete (or blaſyng Starre) ſhould now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare euen whileſt that wee are rocked in the Cradle of ſynne and ſecuritie, and are whollie giuen vnto all maner of abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: to premoniſhe and forewarne vs of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terclappes (that is to ſaie) to threaten, and prognoſticate condigne puniſhemente, to light vpon all perſones generally, who daie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and howerly doe (of let purpoſe and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, wilfully offende, Gods diuine Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie) and doe continually wallow and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in their wicked and abhominable ſynne and tranſgreſſion. For whiche cauſe Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God would haue as well Prince as people, to looke into their former abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable and ſinfull liues: And when thei haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered the horror and lothſomneſſe therof, forthwith to frame their hartes, and to prepare their mindes, to be earneſtly pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and ſorowfull for the ſame. And wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as before, we can not deny, but that euery one of vs hath erred and gone aſtraie, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the higheſt vnto the loweſt (yea, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
<pb facs="tcp:17687:34"/> Prieſte, to the Prophete,) haue been ſo ſecure and careleſſe of our dueties, that we haue wilfully contemned, the Iudgemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of GOD threatned againſt vs, by his faithfull Preachers and Miniſters: knowe you therefore (deare Chriſtians) that it is now the good purpoſe, and diuine pleaſure of almightie God: (aſwell by this burnyng Comete, whiche now appeareth: as alſo, by the late dreadfull yearthquake, but moſte cheefly by that ſupernaturall Starre of all others, that was ſeene in <hi>Caſſiopeia,</hi> with other ſuche ſtrange and wonderfull ſightes and monſters in Nature) to moue and ſtirr vp all the ſorte of vs (beeyng moſte wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and miſerable ſinners) to be mindfull of the Iudgement daie. And beforehande to examine and rippe vp, euery manne his owne harte and conſcience, and diligently to ſeeke, and ſearch the cauſes of the wrath of almightie GOD in our owne ſelues by the reaſon of our manifold and greuous ſinnes: and hauyng founde the cauſe of his heauie diſpleaſure againſt vs, to bee in our owne rebellious Nature, wee ought euery one of vs to iudge our ſelues, that wee bee
<pb facs="tcp:17687:35"/> not Iudged of the Lorde. And albeeit ſome doe offende his diuine Maieſtie, more gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly then other ſome: yet would not our good and gracious God haue any of vs all, to eſteeme hymſelf to bee free from blame, either voide of ſinne: But rather (as before I haue declared) he would haue vs euery one with all expedition, to renounce our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer wickedneſſe. And by bowyng our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues doune before his Tribunall ſeate, and ſtoupyng vnder the mightie ſcepter of his kyngdome, he would haue vs confeſſe, that wee haue all ſinned. And by our faithfull repentaunce, and vnfeigned conuerſion vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his diuine Maieſtie, (in wepyng, faſting and mournyng) to preuente the ſharpe ſworde, and the ſmart roddes and whippes whiche he hath in his iuſte iudgement pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared in a readineſſe, for to whippe and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe vs withall, if wee goe onwardes in our former rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as we haue doen here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore. Therfore let euery man, or woman of what conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo euer thei be, apply that, whiche hetherto hath been ſpoken vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, and knowe this for an vndoubted truthe, that albeeit we haue deſerued to bee
<pb facs="tcp:17687:35"/> vtterly cutte of and deſtroied, by the ſharpe ſworde of Gods diuine indignation: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit theſe vnwo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted and ſtrange ſignes and tokens, whiche he ſendeth daiely emongeſt vs (bothe in the Sonne and in the Moone, and the Starres, and in all liuyng creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res) bee preſages of his heauy diſpleaſure, that he hath taken againſt vs, and alſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table forewarnynges of a moſte greeuous calamitie and deſtruction, that he ſhall in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie and righteouſneſſe bryng vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, by the reaſon of our filthie ſinnes: yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng, if that we will but euen in this the daie of his louyng and mercifull viſitation, tourne vnto hym with all our ſoule: If ſo bee that to daie we will heare his voice, and not harden our hartes, &amp;c: If ſo be (as Ioel ſaieth) that we will rent our hartes, and not our garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, and turne now vnfeignedly vnto the Lorde: we ſhall finde hym ſo mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull &amp; louyng a God, that he will receiue vs againe into his fauour. Yea he will be ſo glad of our conuerſion, and amendement of life, that he will haue compaſſion vpon vs (if he ſee vs truely penitent) naie he will fall vpon our neckes and kiſſe vs, and bring
<pb facs="tcp:17687:36"/> forthe the beſte coate, and put it on vs: and putte a ryng on our hande, and Shooes on our feete, and kill the fatte Calfe for vs, and make vs merie, after that he hath receiued vs home vnto hymſelf ſaffe and ſound: (that is to ſaie) whereas heretofore we were eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deade by the reaſon of ſinne and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, he will make vs aliue againe, and quicken vs by the Reſurrection of Chriſte Ieſus. And whereas wee haue hetherto wandred verie farre, and gone aſtraie like loſte Sheepe: he of his fatherly kindeneſſe and mercie, will bryng vs home againe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his backe vnto the Sheepefolde of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, who is the cheef Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe and Shepherd of our ſoules, vnto whom with the Father, and the holie ghoſt, three perſones and one God bee all praiſe and dominion for euer. <hi>AMEN.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17687:36"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
